Andreea Bobu

70 Vassar Street, 31-245 – Cambridge, MA 02142 $\bf \cong$ (617)-417-0993 • $\bf \boxtimes$ abobu@mit.edu • ' $\bf \cong$ www.mit.edu/~abobu

Research Interests

I develop autonomous agents that learn to do tasks for, with, and around humans. My goal is to ensure that these agents align with people, whether expert designers or novice end users. My work looks at: 1) getting the right data to supervise the training of the robot, whether directly from people or via priors; 2) enabling agents and humans to efficiently and interactively arrive at shared task representations for reliable interaction; 3) quantifying and addressing misalignment caused by different human modeling choices. I ground my work in experiments and user studies with AI systems like assistive robot arms or LLM agents, and draw upon methods from deep learning, mathematical human modeling, inverse reinforcement learning, and Bayesian inference.

Professional Positions

2024-present Boeing Assistant Professor

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics

2023–2024 Research Scientist

The AI Institute

Summer 2021 Research Intern

NVIDIA Research, Robotics Group

Education

2017-2023 University of California, Berkeley

Ph.D. in Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences

Advisor: Anca Dragan

Thesis: Aligning Robot Representations with Humans

2013–2017 Massachusetts Institute of Technology

B.S. in Computer Science and Engineering, Minor in Mathematics

Advisors: Adrian Dalca, Polina Golland, Stefanie Jegelka

Awards and Honors

- 2023 Emerging Research Award at the Intl. Symposium on Mathematics of Neuroscience For the talk on "Aligning Robot and Human Representations".
- 2022 Rising Stars Academic Career Workshop in EECS

Chosen to participate in an intensive workshop for historically marginalized graduate students and postdocs who are interested in pursuing academic careers in EE, CS, and AI and decision-making.

2022 Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS) Pioneers

Selected for workshop bringing together top early career researchers in robotics.

- 2021 Apple PhD Scholars in Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning Fellowship

 Two-year fellowship with an annual stipend of \$45,000 for graduate students in AI/ML.
- 2021 Best Paper Award Finalist at ACM/IEEE HRI

For the paper "Feature Expansive Reward Learning: Rethinking Human Input".

2021 Best Paper Award Honorable Mention at IEEE T-RO

For the paper "Quantifying Hypothesis Space Misspecification in Learning From Human-Robot Demonstrations and Physical Corrections".

2020 Best Paper Award Winner at ACM/IEEE HRI

For the paper "LESS is More: Rethinking Probabilistic Models of Human Behavior".

2020 Human-Robot Interaction (HRI) Pioneers

Chosen to participate in a highly selective workshop seeking to foster creativity, communication, and collaboration across Human-Robot Interaction.

2019 Cadence Women in Technology Scholarship

A \$5,000 scholarship for women in EECS demonstrating leadership and a strong academic record.

2016 Best Paper Award Winner at MICCAI Patch-MI

For the paper "Patch-Based Discrete Registration of Clinical Brain Images".

2016 Google Anita Borg Memorial Scholarship

A \$10,000 scholarship for women in EECS demonstrating leadership and a strong academic record.

2015-present Member of Tau Beta Pi (TBP) National Honor Society for Engineering

Honors society for engineering students with the strongest academic records at their university.

2015-present Member of Eta Kappa Nu (HKN) National Honor Society for EECS

Honors society for EECS students with the strongest academic records at their university.

Teaching

Fall 2024 16.410/16.413: Principles of Autonomy and Decision Making

MIT

Instructor

Spring 2021 CS 287H: Algorithmic Human-Robot Interaction

UC Berkeley

Graduate Student Instructor

Fall 2019 CS 188: Introduction to Artificial Intelligence

UC Berkelev

Graduate Student Instructor

January 2016 6.178: Introduction to Software Engineering in Java

MIT

Instructor and Lecturer

2015–2017 6.046: Design and Analysis of Algorithms

MIT

Spring 2014 6.01: Introduction to Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

MIT

Student Lab Assistant

Advising & Mentoring

Current Ph.D. Students

Minyoung Hwang

Past M.S. Students

Regina Wang (\rightarrow M.S. at Stanford), Yi Liu (\rightarrow ML Research Engineer at Scale AI), Arjun Sripathy (\rightarrow Senior ML Scientist at Tesla Autopilot)

Past Undergraduate Students

David Zhang (\rightarrow Codepoint Fellow), Matthew Zurek (\rightarrow Ph.D. at UW-Madison), Sampada Deglurkar (\rightarrow Ph.D. at UC Berkeley)

Ph.D. Committees

Sean Ye (Georgia Tech), Alex Forsey-Smerek (MIT)

Outreach

Summer 2024 RoboLaunch

CMU

I gave a talk at the CMU RI RoboLaunch Speaker Series, an outreach program for promoting robotics & AI research and education.

Summer 2019 Girls in Engineering Camp

UC Berkeley

Lecturer and Mentor

I co-organized a Self-Driving Cars workshop, teaching the girls about sensing, planning, and control in autonomous driving, and experimenting with an Evo robot.

August 2018 AI4ALL UC Berkeley Teaching Assistant I mentored a team of underrepresented high school students as they learned to train a deep reinforcement learning agent in MuJoCo. 2018–2022 Berkeley Artificial Intelligence Research UC Berkelev Mentor I mentored underrepresented undergraduate students in research and career planning. 2018–2019 Women in Computer Science and Engineering UC Berkeley Mentor I mentored early-stage female PhD students in career planning and navigating life at UC Berkeley. 2016 Women in Science and Engineering MITMentor I mentored high school girls from the Greater Boston area during monthly sessions designed to introduce them to engineering at MIT. 2013–2015 Educational Studies Program MIT Lecturer I taught courses on "Water Security in Asia", "Introduction to Probability", and "Group Theory" to middle school students in the New England region. Professional Activities Conference Area Chair 2024 CoRL: Conference on Robot Learning 2023 ICLR: International Conference on Learning Representations Workshops & Seminars Co-organized 2024 Workshop on Task Specification for General-Purpose Intelligent Robots R:SS2024 Workshop on Mechanisms for Mapping Human Input to Robots R:SS2024 6th Workshop on Long-term Human Motion Prediction ICRA2024 6th Workshop on Lifelong Learning and Personalization in Long-Term HRI HRI2023 Workshop on Interactive Learning with Implicit Human Feedback ICML2022 Workshop on Aligning Robot Representations with Humans CoRL2022–2023 Dream/CPAR Seminar UC Berkeley 2022 2nd Workshop on Social Intelligence in Humans and Robots R:SS2021 1st Workshop on Social Intelligence in Humans and Robots ICRA2020 Workshop on Advances and Challenges in Imitation Learning for Robotics R:SS2020–2021 SemiAutonomous Vehicles Seminar UC Berkeley External Reviewer for Workshops, Conferences, Journals, and Grant Panels Robotics: Corl, ICRA, R:SS, HRI, IROS, L4DC, RA-L, T-RO, T-MECH, T-HRI Machine Learning: NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, Nature: Machine Intelligence Grant Panels: NSF CISE and FRR Selected Invited Talks Why Robots Aren't Superhuman in Our Human World 2024 TEDx MITAligning Robot and Human Representations 2024 Autonomy Talks ETH2024 6.161: Robotics Science & Systems MIT2024 16-886: Models & Algorithms for Interactive Robotics CMU2023 International Symposium on the Mathematics of Neuroscience ISMoN

2023	Center for Human-Compatible AI Workshop		CHAI
2023	Stanford Robotics Seminar		Stanford
2023	Department Seminar MI	T, Princeton, Georgia Tech, Cornell, Brown, NYU,	UIUC, UCSD
2022	UW Robotics Colloquium		UW
2022	New Trends in Aerospace Seminar Series		MIT
2022	CS 6960: Human-AI Alignment		U of Utah
	Inducing Structure in Robot Learning via Human-Guided Representations		
2022	SemiAutonomous Vehicles Seminar		UC Berkeley
2021	Workshop on Aware Learning: How to Benefit from Priors		CDC
2021	Workshop on Human-AI Collaboration in Sequential Decision-Making		ICML
2021	Human And Robot Partners (HARP) Lab Reading Group		CMU
2021	CS287H: Algorithmic Foundations of Human-Robot Interaction		UC Berkeley
	Journal Articles		
[J3]	9 1	by Bootstrapping from Human Queries Sundaralingam, V.W. Chao, M. Cakmak, D. E.	lov

A. Bobu, C. Paxton, W. Yang, B. Sundaralingam, Y.W. Chao, M. Cakmak, D. Fox. IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L), 2022.

[J2] Inducing Structure in Reward Learning via Feature Learning A. Bobu, M. Wiggert, C. Tomlin, A. D. Dragan. The International Journal of Robotics Research (IJRR), 2022.

[J1] Quantifying Hypothesis Space Misspecification in Learning from Human-Robot **Demonstrations and Physical Corrections** A. Bobu, A. Bajcsy, J. F. Fisac, S. Deglurkar, A. D. Dragan. IEEE Transactions on Robotics (T-RO), 2019. Best paper award honorable mention.

Conference Publications

- [12] Adaptive Language-Guided Abstraction from Contrastive Explanations A. Peng, B. Z. Li, I. Sucholutsky, N. Kumar, J. A. Shah, J. Andreas, A. Bobu Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL), 2024. (in review)
- [11] Preference-Conditioned Language-Guided Abstraction A. Peng, A. Bobu, B. Z. Li, T. R. Sumers, I. Sucholutsky, N. Kumar, T. L. Griffiths, J. A. Shah ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI), 2024.
- [10] Aligning Robot and Human Representations **A.** Bobu^{*}, A. Peng^{*}, P. Agrawal, J. A. Shah, and A. D. Dragan. ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI), 2024.
- [9] Diagnosing and Repairing Feature Representations Under Distribution Shifts I. Lourenço, A. Bobu, C. R. Rojas, B. Wahlberg. IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2023.
- [8] Diagnosis, Feedback, Adaptation: A Human-in-the-Loop Framework for Test-Time **Policy Adaptation** A. Peng, A. Netanyahu, M. K. Ho, T. Shu, A. Bobu, J. A. Shah, P. Agrawal. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2023.
- [7] SIRL: Similarity-based Implicit Representation Learning A. Bobu^{*}, Y. Liu^{*}, R. Shah, D. S. Brown, and A. D. Dragan. ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human Robot Interaction (HRI), 2023.
- [6] Teaching Robots to Span the Space of Functional Expressive Motion A. Sripathy, A. Bobu, Z. Li, K. Sreenath, D. S. Brown, and A. D. Dragan. IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), 2022.

- [5] Dynamically Switching Human Prediction Models for Efficient Planning A. Sripathy*, A. Bobu*, D. S. Brown, A. D. Dragan.

 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2021.
- [4] Situational Confidence Assistance for Lifelong Shared Autonomy M. Zurek*, A. Bobu*, D. S. Brown, A. D. Dragan.

 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), 2021.
- [3] Feature Expansive Reward Learning: Rethinking Human Input A. Bobu*, M. Wiggert*, C. Tomlin, A. D. Dragan.

 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human Robot Interaction (HRI), 2021.

 Best paper award finalist.
- [2] LESS is More: Rethinking Probabilistic Models of Human Behavior A. Bobu*, D. Scobee*, J. F. Fisac, S. Sastry, A. D. Dragan.

 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human Robot Interaction (HRI), 2020.

 Best paper award winner.
- [1] Learning Under Misspecified Objective Spaces A. Bobu, A. Bajcsy, J. F. Fisac, A. D. Dragan. Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL), 2018.

 Invited to special issue.

Workshop Publications

- [W7] Getting Aligned on Representational Alignment
 I. Sucholutsky, L. Muttenthaler, A. Weller, A. Peng, A. Bobu, B. Kim, B. C. Love, E. Grant,
 I. Groen, J. Achterberg, J. B. Tenenbaum, K. M. Collins, K. L. Hermann, K. Oktar, K. Greff,
 M. N. Hebart, N. Jacoby, Q. Zhang, R. Marjieh, R. Geirhos, S. Chen, S. Kornblith, S. Rane, T.
 Konkle, T. P. O'Connell, T. Unterthiner, A. K. Lampinen, K. Muller, M. Toneva, T. L. Griffiths
 Workshop on Representational Alignment (Re-Align), ICLR 2024.
- [W6] Time-Efficient Reward Learning via Visually Assisted Cluster Ranking D. Zhang, M. Carroll, A. Bobu, A. D. Dragan. Workshop on Human-in-the-Loop Learning, NeurIPS 2022.
- [W5] Efficient Robot Teaching by Learning Intermediate Human-Guided Representations A. Bobu.
 Companion of the Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS), 2022.
- [W4] Aligning Robot Representations with Humans
 A. Bobu, A. Peng.
 Workshop on Collaborative Robots and the Work of the Future, ICRA 2022.
- [W3] Detecting Hypothesis Space Misspecification in Robot Learning from Human Input A. Bobu, A. D. Dragan. Companion of the ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction, 2020.
- [W2] Adapting to Continuously Shifting Domains
 A. Bobu, E. Tzeng, J. Hoffman, T. Darrell.
 Workshop at the International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2018.
- [W1] Patch-Based Discrete Registration of Clinical Brain Images A. V. Dalca, A. Bobu, N. S. Rost, P. Golland. Patch-based Techniques in Medical Imaging (MICCAI Patch-MI), 2016. Best paper award winner.

Patents

Concept Training Technique for Machine Learning

A. Bobu, B. Sundaralingam, C. Paxton, M. Cakmak, W. Yang, Y. Chao, D. Fox. U.S. Patent 17982401.